Okay, בוקר טוב, Boker Tov, welcome back to me I guess.
We pick up on the bottom of קי"א עמוד ב'. Kuf-Yud-Aleph Amud-Bet.
We're in the section where we're dealing with the obligations and the
prohibitions of not to postpone the payment of a worker. ביומו תתן
שכרו, Bayomo titein secharo, pay him on his day, which חז"ל Chazal
basically understood to mean if he's a day worker you have the
night to pay him with, if he's a night worker you have
the next day to pay him for. Because there are two verses.
One says, לא תלין פעולת שכיר אתך עד בוקר, Lo talin peulat
sachir itecha ad boker,
don't let it sleep overnight, which means make sure it gets paid
before the next morning. And the other one is ביומו תתן שכרו
ולא תבוא עליו השמש, Bayomo titein secharo velo tavo elav hashemesh,
pay it during the day and don't let the sun set. So
the גמרא Gemara says it refers to if you're a night worker
pay it the following day, if you're a day worker pay it
the following night, and those are the various מצוות. mitzvot. Once that
you transgress that prohibition once, you can't transgress it again, so then
there becomes what the rabbis understand sounds like a rabbinic מצווה mitzvah
of לא תשהא. Lo tishahe. After you've transgressed it once you still
obviously have an obligation to pay it as quickly as possible. So
that's the basic framework. Already have a question? Hold on. That's the
basic framework. But then the גמרא Gemara goes on to speak about
two things that are not explicit in the פסוקים, pesukim, because one
is the verse refers to מאחיך, me’achecha, your brother. So it says
it really isn't limited to your brother, it even applies to a
גר תושב. ger toshav. Again, this is sort of independent from an
issue that the גמרא Gemara dealt with just at the end of
yesterday, which is always a very challenging problematic issue in terms of
is there or what is the nature of the prohibition in terms
of stealing. But here we're talking about no no no stealing we're
not talking about, certainly wouldn't apply to a case of a גר
תושב, ger toshav, but the question is nevertheless do you have a
special מצווה mitzvah to pay on a timely basis. So it learns
from the word of אחיך achecha that you do, no not from
אחיך, achecha, from an extra word that you do that this מצווה
mitzvah of paying on a timely basis also doesn't apply to non-Jews,
applies to גר תושב. ger toshav. And learns from other words that
it applies not only when you're hiring somebody's labor, but even when
you basically are renting their vessels and their animals. Which is I
think a definite, I mean both of those are big חידושים. chidushim.
One is just the simple sense of the verse אחיך achecha which
seems to be limited to fellow Jew. So it's interesting that חז"ל
Chazal go out of their way to include a non-Jew here, at
least a גר תושב. ger toshav. And also the idea because at
the end of the פסוק, pasuk, which we'll get to in a
minute, says ואליו הוא נושא
את נפשו, ve’elav hu nosei et nafsho, person the sense that I
risk my life or I put in all this effort and that
poignancy of how much I've been working the whole day and I
go home empty-handed and so on, it's not the same when I
rent out my vessels and my animals. Sure I'm trying to make
money and maybe I even need it to put some food on
the table, but the same sort of sharpness of the verse and
the poignancy of that sense of risking your life, your sense of
like you've worked the whole day and now you're not going to
get paid, there is obviously it doesn't apply to the same degree.
And nevertheless that's included in the verses as well, even if you're
renting out your vessels or your animals, you also the obligation is
to pay within the next sort of time period. Yes? No. So
I'm baffled by that whole thing even
that we're dividing it by if it's by a daily or it
was a nightly worker. I mean that's also again somewhat read into
it because the whole thing about ביומו תתן שכרו bayomo titein secharo
is clearly about שכר עני ואביון. sechar ani ve'evyon. That's how the
פסוק pasuk begins at that point. Right. לא תעשוק שכר עני ואביון
מאחיך או מגרך Lo ta'ashok sechar ani ve'evyon me'achecha o migercha then
ביומו תתן שכרו bayomo titein secharo וגם כי עני הוא vegam ki
ani hu ואליו הוא נושא נפשו. ve’elav hu nosei nafsho.
That's why it's like to at least to me what it's trying
to say is that it's a bigger injustice if you do this
to a poor person. Right. So but then we read oh no
one is for the day one is for the night. I mean
like that doesn't compromise the sense of the injustice. It's always an
injustice, but the question is you also have to give the בעל
הבית ba’al habayis a time to pay and you're dealing with a
contradiction between פסוקים. pesukim. I don't really see that as sort of
problematic. But the important point there is to make which the גמרא
Gemara does make, or I'm getting lost because I was catching up
whether it made it yet or it's going to make it today,
is that who logically would this apply even not to a poor
person? Suppose you're not poor and but you're still I have a
job, pays me nicely, pays me whatever it does per maybe it's
per day, it gets into this question in the משנה mishnah right,
what if it's per week, per year, for whatever? You don't have
to be poor to still have a right to be paid on
time. All those Jewish schools that pay their teacher pay it late,
right? How are they not transgressing this prohibition? And so maybe it
doesn't mean they're rich but it doesn't mean they're poor either. Nevertheless
these פסוקים pesukim still apply even not in the case of עני.
ani. Okay let's continue now in the גמרא. Gemara. So the גמרא
Gemara in the middle of figuring out all of these issues of
how you include these various things wants to know what do you
learn from this word in the פסוק, pasuk, what do you learn
from that word in the פסוק. pasuk. So the גמרא Gemara picks
up with the following, two
second wide line at the bottom of קי"א עמוד ב'. kuf-yud-aleph amud-bet.
רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה Rabbi Yose b'rabi Yehuda האי לא תלין פעולת
שכיר אתך עד בוקר מאי עביד ליה? hai lo talin peulat sachir
itecha ad boker mai avid lei? What does he do with the
word
אתך? itecha? Right, what does he do with that extra sense
of because before we learned that אתך itecha includes even vessels and
animals that you rent out but he doesn't say that. So what
does he do with that extra word? So the גמרא... Gemara... ...like
what Rabbi Assi says. דאמר רבי אסי d'amar rabi Assi אפילו לא
שכרו אלא לבצור לו אשכול אחד של ענבים afilu lo secharo ela
livtzor lo eshkol echad shel anavim עובר משום בל תלין over mishum
bal talin
that even if it's a very small small thing right just for
hours you know it doesn't even apply for a day or even
if a very small type of עבודה avodah nevertheless you transgress בל
תלין bal talin you know question is why that's such a חידוש
chidush even just one אשכול eshkol תוספות Tosafot sort of reminds us
of an earlier גמרא Gemara you might remember this about the permission
of the worker to eat when he is working working
says even if you only hire the guy to harvest one clump
of grapes he can eat that clump that you harvested today that
you've paid him for so now he gets to eat it and
if you don't pay him for it you transgress ביומו תתן שכרו
b'yomo titein secharo you know ולא תלין פעולת שכיר אתך עד בוקר.
v'lo talin peulat sachir itcha ad boker. Okay so let's take a
look ואידך v'idach the other one would say ואליו הוא נושא את
נפשו נפקא. v'elav hu nosei et nafsho nafka.
No
no you learn that out from something that he gives his soul
towards דבר המוסר נפשו עליו davar hamoser nafsho alav anything that he
sort of you know invests effort for so you don't need the
word אתך itcha you can learn that from something else even a
very small type of עבודה avodah this still applies to ואידך v'idach
and the other one who what does he do with this פסוק
pasuk ואליו הוא נושא את נפשו v'elav hu nosei et nafsho you
know that's more like the מוסר mussar part of the פסוק pasuk
the reason part of the פסוק pasuk it's not necessarily clear you
would apply it for a halachic purpose so if so if you
don't need it for a halachic purpose what do you do with
it so here it says let's see what he says then he's
actually going to actually apply it not for a halachic purpose what
if he do with this not to say something halachic but to
tell you the basic מוסר mussar of the
פסוק pasuk okay מבעי ליה לכדתניא miba'ei leh l'chadetanya like we taught
in the ברייתא braita ואליו הוא נושא את נפשו v'elav hu nosei
et nafsho מפני מה mipnei mah
what does it mean that he you know you have to you
know he's giving his life for this מפני מה עלה זה בכבש
ונתלה באילן mipnei mah alah zeh b'kevesh v'nitlah b'ilan
why would a person you know go up some ramp you know
go up thirty floors you know to work on some high-rise building
or go harvest stuff at the top of the tree or the
bottom of the ocean you know ומסר עצמו למיתה umassar atzmo l'mitah
is willing to risk their lives לאו
על שכרו lav al secharo is it not for you know and
not for his fee and now you're not going to give him
his fee he risked his life for it so you know that's
again that real poignancy and the side if you look at the
side there's a different גרסא girsa which sort of sharpens it a
little more לאו שתתן לו שכרו lav shetitein lo secharo focusing on
you wasn't it that you should pay him he risked his life
because he was expecting to get paid at the end of the
day how could you think to delay it okay okay now דבר
אחר davar acher another way of reading this ואליו הוא נושא את
נפשו v'elav hu nosei et nafsho didn't we have that already what
was this
דרשה drasha that you know we didn't say it explicitly ומסר עצמו
למיתה umassar atzmo l'mitah right yeah I mean the גמרא Gemara says
no it says המוסר נפשו עליו hamoser nafsho alav no but anyway
but now we're just explaining you know yes I mean that's פשט
pshat of the פסוק pasuk but it's just elaborating on it okay
דבר אחר davar acher another reading of this verse again you know
not radically different ואליו הוא נושא את נפשו v'elav hu nosei et
nafsho he gives his life for this כל הכובש שכר שכיר kol
hakovesh sechar sachir anybody who you know holds back paying the the
the daily person's servant fee כאילו הוא נוטל נפשו ממנו k'ilu hu
notel nafsho mimenu it's like you have murdered him okay so ואליו
הוא נושא את נפשו v'elav hu nosei et nafsho like for because
meaning because he risked his life and you didn't pay him it's
like he risked his life for nothing it's like you murdered him
or you could just read it if he needs the money to
feed his family and you're not giving the money he needs to
feed his family right he lives off of this it's like you
murdered him I don't know if that's exactly פשט pshat of the
פסוק pasuk but okay now רב הונא
ורב חסדא Rav Huna v'Rav Chisda now the גמרא Gemara has a
debate רב הונא ורב חסדא Rav Huna v'Rav Chisda חד אמר נפשו
של גזלן chad amar nafsho shel gazlan you basically it's like you
know it's like your life will be you're sacrificing your life this
sin is so grievous that it's you know you have to pay
with it for by your
life and calls him here a גזלן gazlan the גמרא Gemara before
said the difference between עושק oshek and גזילה gezeilah and so on
so even though here you're not maybe even refusing to pay him
altogether you're just postponing it's calling him a גזלן gazlan
וחד אמר נפשו של נגזל v'chad amar nafsho shel nigzal no it's
like you took his life the life of the one who you're
stealing from or holding back the money from מאן דאמר נפשו של
גזלן man d'amar nafsho shel gazlan it's like you sacrificed your own
life you know this was sort of a you know a what
do you call it a capital crime דכתיב dichtiv the verse says
אל תגזל דל כי דל הוא al tigzol dal ki dal hu
do not steal from the poor person he because he is poor
and does because he is poor mean that's why you shouldn't steal
from him or don't don't think you can steal from him because
he is poor and therefore you can get away with it and
nobody will come to protect him okay that's the way רש"י Rashi
reads it don't think that you'll be able to get away with
it ואל תדכא עני בשער v'al tedakei ani basha'ar do not trample
down on the poor person in the gate in the city gate
דכתיב dichtiv and it says כי ה' יריב ריבם ki Hashem yariv
rivam because God will come to their defense don't think you can
get away with it they're poor nobody cares about them no God
will come to fight their fight וקבע את קובעיהם נפש v'kava et
koveihem nafesh and take from the spoilers God will despoil the soul
of their despoilers so therefore God will basically take the soul of
those that
steal. Yeah, I don't know, it was very hard to read. Yeah,
let's read a little bit more. It's hard to still read in
the פסוק. pasuk. ומה דאמר נפשו של נגזל, Umah d'amar nafsho shel
nigzal,
no, no, it's like you took his life, דכתיב, d'chtiv, כן ארחות
כל בצע בצע, kein orchot kol botzea batza,
this is the way of all of those who, you know, בצע
batza could mean like ill-gotten gain, but you know maybe and here
presumably means to steal, את נפש בעליו יקח, et nefesh be'alav yikach,
you take the soul of the owners. You steal from somebody, it's
like you stole their soul. So here it's not about risking their
lives, it's about taking something that, you know, is needed for to
sustain a poor person, okay? And therefore you're robbing them of their
life, of their sustenance. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says, ואידך נמי
הא כתיב את נפש בעליו יקח. ve'idach nami ha ktiv et nefesh
be'alav yikach. What do you do with the fact that if you
say it's like you killed the poor person, what do you do
with the, I'm sorry, I'm sorry, if you say it's like you
did a capital crime, you sacrificed your own life, what do you
do with this פסוק pasuk that says that when you do something
like this it's like you killed the poor person? So the גמרא
Gemara says, בבעליו
דהשתא. beva'alav dehashta.
No, no, it means the current owner. You're now the owner because
you stole the money. So את נפש בעליו יקח, et nefesh be'alav
yikach, you're taking your own life if you try to steal from
the poor person. ואידך נמי הא כתיב וקבע את קובעיהם נפש. ve'idach
nami ha ktiv vekava et koveihem nafesh. If you say it's like
you killed the poor person, what about the verse that says God
will come to demand the soul of those that rob from the
poor? So מה טעם קאמר. mah ta'am ka'amar. What's the reason? מה
טעם קובע את קובעיהם, mah ta'am kova et koveihem,
why does God come to punish the stealers, משום דנטלו נפש, mishum
d'natlu nafesh, because they stole, took the, if they killed the poor
person. Of course you could say the פסוקים pesukim are sort of
saying both, but of course we want to emphasize one. So one
wants to sort of say look how terrible it is, it's like
you killed this person, right? And some people, you know, that doesn't
work for everybody, like you know, people that really are just like,
you know, שלי שלי ושלך שלך, sheli sheli veshelach shelach, no, people
that basically look at the whole world that the goal is to
serve their own personal interests or whatever, saying "Oh my god, it's
like you're going to kill this person," like, "What do I care?"
Right? But oh, you know, so some will make it personal. Okay
then, you're going to, your life will get taken. "Oh, okay, why
didn't you say so?" You know? So other people work the opposite
way, like you know these types of פשט, peshat, like, "Oh you
know, it's so terrible your life is going to be," more works
if you sort of speak to my empathy and you try to
make me understand, you know, the impact it has on the other
people. So obviously these are not mutually exclusive, and neither of them
I think are פשט peshat of the פסוקים. pesukim. I think the
first thing the גמרא Gemara says is פשט peshat of the פסוקים,
pesukim, but nevertheless גמרא's Gemara using this as an opportunity. The first
thing, that the guy risks his life to go earn the money,
you know? But anyway, but either way the גמרא's Gemara using this
as an opportunity to do a little מוסר mussar around this מצוה.
mitzvah. Yes, Rabbi Zev. But actually the פשט, peshat, like the term
לקבוע likboa here, is kind of like we say in English idiomatically,
like "I'll fix you," like "I'll fix you." Yeah, like לקבוע likboa
means to, right. Maybe. I have, look, I'm not, I don't know,
I think לקבוע, likboa, I think it normally in this means, I
mean, I don't know, I don't know the etymological root. I think
normally it means like to despoil, you know, to, to steal essentially,
something like that. But, but I don't know, I don't know the
etymological root. But yeah, isn't that the same concept with the orphan
and the widow, and if you don't, then I'll make you an
orphan and a widow? That's a good point. It's echoing, that's a
very good point, that's echoing those פסוקים, pesukim, right. If you try
to oppress them, you, your children, you know, will become orphans, your
wife will become a widow. יישר כח. yashar koach. Okay, back to
הלכה. halacha. אימתי בזמן שתבעו לא תבעו אינו עובר עליו. Eimatai bizman
sheteva'o lo teva'o eino over alav.
When are you transgressed? When does the clock essentially start ticking? Only
if the guy says, "Please pay me." But if he sort of
doesn't wait to be paid, you know, if he doesn't ask to
be paid, then you don't transgress. You only transgress once the demand
is, you know, the clock starts ticking once the demand is made,
which is a little bit funny because you know given the power
dynamics of the whole thing, you can easily imagine that somebody doesn't
want to go to their boss at the end of the day
and say, "Please pay me." I'm going to nudge him too much
and then he's going to threaten to fire me and this and
that, right? So it's not always like just because you're not asking
to be paid means that you're okay with waiting, right? So that's
a, it's a very interesting
הלכה. halacha. תנו רבנן לא תלין פעולת שכיר יכול אפילו לא תבעו
תלמוד לומר אתך לדעתך. Tanu rabanan lo talin pe'ulat sachir yakhol afilu
lo teva'o talmud lomar itcha l'da'atcha. Don't let it rest with you,
לדעתך, l'da'atcha, you're the one choosing not to pay it. Okay? But
if basically he hasn't asked to be paid yet, fine, then I'm,
it's not my choice. He hasn't, he's the one, he could have
come to get it. I understand, but that's the דרשה. drasha. The
דרשה drasha is basically it's if you're the one holding it back
and as opposed to when he is implicitly okay with you to
hold it. But again, I mean, to me it would make a
lot more sense if the person would explicitly give you permission. That's
one thing. But the sort of the absence of asking for it
is seen as being okay with waiting seems very strange given the
power dynamics. Okay. יכול אפילו אין לו. Yakhol afilu ein lo. So
now, maybe this, now it's very interesting you know the way the
גמרא... Gemara... Okay, וכלה אפילו אין לו. v'kala afilu ein lo. So
now, maybe this is now it's very interesting the way the פסוקי,
psukei, the גמרא Gemara here and the הלכה halacha here is like
sensitive to the employer and not just the employee. You know, the
תורה Torah is very clear in terms of the moral message, right?
Pay in during the day. Not only that, like what when you're
talking about פשט הפסוקים pshat hapsukim what I thought you were going
to say is that I even think that the פשט הפסוקים pshat
hapsukim is that if this guy worked for me today, I have
to pay him before the day is over. I don't even have
the following night, right? You know, so I, you know, he worked
for me today, I better give him his salary before the day
is out on the very same time that he's working, the end
of the time he's working. So but the גמרא Gemara creates this
whole balancing, one minute, you know, I've got to give the guy
a little time. I mean, I'm not saying this the גמרא Gemara
explicitly said this, but this is, you know, my understanding. How does
the גמרא Gemara read it that they have the next time period?
I mean, come on, you know, look at it from the employer's
perspective. What, I have to pay everybody immediately before the day ends?
I mean, they just finished work a minute ago. Okay, you know
what, give me a little time. Why, you know, let's say they
they haven't asked for it yet, okay? If they haven't asked, you
don't, you're not over yet. Let's say I don't have the money
available. Okay, I understand, I'm just saying it's very interesting and I
don't think I wouldn't frame it as a, you know, we're going
to get to this, I think we're starting to get to... but
anyway, in a minute, I wouldn't say necessarily oh, you know, חז"ל
Chazal are more employer-friendly and the תורה, Torah, you know, like חז"ל
Chazal are the Republicans and the תורה Torah is the Democrats, or
whatever, you know, the תורה Torah is more the employee-friendly. I think
the תורה, Torah, with the way I would read it, is the
תורה Torah is speaking with a very strong moral voice and חז"ל
Chazal are trying to be sensitive to the real dynamics of the
commercial life, you know, and if you make demands that are too
unreasonable on the employers, right, everybody is going to suffer, right? There's
a reason, like if you made twenty dollars minimum wage, you could
say oh, that'd be great for the poor, it wouldn't be great
for the poor, nobody would get a job, you know? So there's
a reality of finding the right... what? That sounds like a Republican.
You see? There's got to be a limit. There's a reason there's
not a hundred-dollar minimum wage, right? There's a certain point where you've
got to strike a balance between, you know, sort of this, this
sensitivity for the employees and a workable type of an economic system.
So that's I think a little bit of what we're seeing taking
place here. So let's read a little bit more of this. So,
okay, יכול אפילו אין
לו. yakhol afilu ein lo.
Maybe even if you don't have the money you transgress. Michael says
why not? Don't hire them if you don't have the money. But
תלמוד לומר אתך. talmud lomar itcha. Don't keep it with you. It's
not with you if you don't have the money at all. שיש
אתך, sheyesh itcha, that you have. He's as asset rich and cash
poor. Do we not learn anything? I mean like I could wait
forever and not be over? Right, so that's the question. Are you
over on this sort of rabbinic בל תשהה bal tisheheh type of
a thing? The other question is what does it mean have the
money? Could I, I've got to call up my, my, you know,
my what's it guy? My no, not my loan shark, the guy
who I handle my, my tax, my broker, and tell him to
liquidate some stocks and have the money ready by the end of
the day, but I don't want to do that, right? I don't
want to liquidate those stocks. So what does it mean that you
have the money available, cash? You know? So that's also a question.
Okay,
שיש אתך. sheyesh itcha. יכול
אפילו המחהו אצל חנווני. yakhol afilu himchehu eitzel chanuani. Maybe even if
you directed him to the storekeeper and said the storekeeper now is
going to pay him. Now there's also an interesting question. He gets
to decide that the storekeeper's going to pay you and not me.
So תוספות Tosafot actually in a couple of the תוספותין Tosafotin he
reads it with the assumption that the poor person asked for or
agreed to, you know, or minimally agreed to get paid by the
storekeeper. You know, I mean I assume that if you hire me
and in the middle of the day you say I'm not going
to pay you cash, I'm gonna have the storekeeper, that you're not
allowed to do. But if I asked for it, or if at
the time of employment you say to me look, I don't, you
know, I have an arrangement with the storekeeper, that's going to be
your pay, and I agree under those terms, right, so then that
would be, that would be the terms I agreed to. So יכול
אפילו המחהו אצל חנווני ואצל שולחני. yakhol afilu himchehu eitzel chanuani v'eitzel
shulchani. Maybe even if you had somebody else to pay, the storekeeper,
the moneychanger, and they postponed, maybe you would
transgress. תלמוד לומר אתך. talmud lomar itcha. No, no, no, you have
to be holding the money by you. It has to be you
that you're not, you're not paying. לא המחהו אצל חנווני ואצל שולחני,
lo himchehu eitzel chanuani v'eitzel shulchani, not when it's somebody else's responsibility
to pay and they don't transgress because they're not the ones who
they worked for. So this is a way you could get out
of ever transgressing, you know, which the גמרא Gemara dealt with earlier.
You could just make an arrangement with a friend, you know, you'll
pay and, you know, for my workers, I'll pay for your workers.
It's like some people do when it comes to, you know, their
kids' tuition. גמילות חסד של אמת. gemilut chesed shel emet. Good word!
You know, these tricky things people do with their kids' tuition. I
give it, you give a donation to my kid's school and it's
tax-deductible for you, and I give a donation to your kid's school.
Yeah, it's
just got to be a little bit, a little bit crafty. Oh
my God, I hope we didn't give anybody any ideas. Anyway, what?
Anyway, but the point is so, and earlier when that came up
in the גמרא, Gemara, right, earlier when... yeah, I hope nobody's watching
at the IRS.
Oh, that's a good idea! Oh God, anyway, you're right, gotta be
careful. You know, because there's the גמרא Gemara problem of their sons
watching on the Daf. Yeah, exactly. Anyway, you know, but the גמרא
Gemara beforehand had that and תוספות Tosafot immediately
explained, חס ושלום, chas v'shalom, that you're trying to not pay on
time. Fine, but you don't want to sometimes, you know, you forget
or whatever, so you want to do that as a as a
safeguard in case you accidentally, you know, slip up that you won't
transgress. But nevertheless, nevertheless, you know, this presents a lot of opportunities,
a lot of loopholes. Dennis, do you have a question before? No?
Okay. All right. So trying to control the sense of the timing.
I just have a problem with it if you don't have it
and you knew you didn't have it, you're not עובר. over. Yeah,
so you have some very good point. You're right, I totally hear
that. How about עובר over a לאו דשחרית lav d'shacharit at least?
Or misleading? Misleading, yeah, that's I mean yeah you're right, גניבת דעת
geneivat da'at something, yeah, it's a good point. Yeah, that's I mean
you're absolutely correct and maybe that's discussed in the פוסקים, poskim, I
would have to look into it. Okay, אם שלחו אצל חנווני ואצל
שולחני אינו עובר. im shelachu etzel chanvani v'etzel shulchani eino over. Now
continuing on in the משנה, Mishnah, the point that we've just learned
the basis for the פסוקים, pesukim, if you directed him to the
storekeeper or to the money changer, you don't transgress. So איבעיא להו,
ibaia lehu, חוזר או אינו חוזר? chozer o eino chozer? Now,
can the... the עני, ani, the worker, decide that he's going to
change his mind or not? Meaning that he's going to say, 'You
know what? I actually would rather not collect from the storekeeper. I
actually would rather you pay me directly, you the בעל הבית.' ba'al
habayit. So this gets into a whole... so the fact that we're
saying that he has a right to be חוזר chozer makes it
clear that the employer can't force him to this arrangement to some
degree, whether he had to either initiate it or at least
agree to it. And now the question is can he back out
in the middle and say, 'Actually I want to get paid by
you, the storekeeper'? Well רש"י Rashi points out, right? What he's pointing
out is he says if the בעל הבית... ba'al habayit... if the
חנווני chanvani vouches... right. Well, that's why it's most important because if
he has the ability to be חוזר, chozer, then if the חנווני
chanvani doesn't have the money, I'll just go back to the בעל
הבית. ba'al habayit. That's clearly why you would want to. And then
the question will become, and תוספות Tosfos actually frames the question, and
תוספות Tosfos has a long discussion what exactly the question is, but
at one point תוספות Tosfos frames the question, yes, he has the
right to be חוזר, chozer, but the question is if he's חוזר,
chozer, will that then make the בעל הבית ba'al habayit transgress? If
the initial arrangement was one that the storekeeper would pay and then,
so let's accept as a fact that the employee can be חוזר.
chozer. If he chooses to be חוזר chozer and now in the
middle of the day I become obligated to pay him, I the
employer directly obligated, can I be עובר over if the original arrangement
was such that it wasn't my obligation? Okay, so that's the way
תוספות Tosfos frames the question. Let's see what the answer is. So
can he be חוזר chozer and what would be the implications of
him being חוזר? chozer? רב ששת Rav Sheshet אמר אינו חוזר, amar
eino chozer, he can't. רבה Rabbah אמר חוזר, amar chozer, he can.
אמר רבה מנא אמינא לה, amar Rabbah mna amina lah, where do
I know that he can be
חוזר? chozer? מדקתני אינו עובר עליו, midekatani eino over alav, that he
does not transgress... the owner doesn't transgress when he doesn't pay him
and has a storekeeper pay. So מעבר הוא דלא עבר הא מהדר
הדר. me'avar hu dela avar ha mahadar hadar. So it sounds like
the storekeeper doesn't transgress but like the עני ani was able to
change the arrangement. Meaning, you know, I think what רבה Rabbah is
basically saying is that if the storekeeper's obligation to pay, of course
the employer doesn't transgress. The only way the משנה Mishnah is interesting
is if what the משנה Mishnah is saying is because of that
initial arrangement, now even though you the employee have changed and you
know have forgone that and you want to be paid by me
directly, I still won't transgress because the original arrangement was that it
was not my responsibility. That's how רבה Rabbah is reading the משנה.
Mishnah. Yes, you're allowed to be חוזר chozer but I still don't
transgress. Right, you don't transgress because enough time has passed when you
thought you were going to get paid by the חנווני. chanvani. Yeah,
because the initial arrangement, it did not start with it being my
responsibility. But as of this moment when he's חוזר chozer five days
later, no, can't be עובר over if you don't pay me? No,
no, that's the way תוספות Tosfos would read it is no, it's
not a... all bets are off. Exactly, once the initial arrangement was
that it wasn't my responsibility, then exactly, then from the perspective of
this הלכה, halachah, I am not the one who has to be
paying on the time. Okay, ורב ששת v'Rav Sheshet אמר לא. amar
lo. מאי אינו עובר אינו בתורת לאו. mai eino over eino b'torat
lav. No, what it means is that there's no way I can
be עובר over because he can't change the deal. So since he
can't change the deal, the employee, of course there's... it's never possible
for me to be עובר over because it's always the חנווני's chanvani
responsibility, not mine. Okay, בעי מיניה מרב ששת, ba'ei minei miRav Sheshet,
קבלנות, kablanut, עובר עליו משום בל תלין או אינו עובר עליו משום
בל תלין? over alav mishum bal talin o eino over alav mishum
bal talin? This is a nice question.
Let's say I hire you for the job and not for a
day, a week, a year, and so on. Okay, you know, I
want you to go ahead and make a cabinet for me. Here's
some wood. You know, we never know when it's going to be
finished. So okay, that's one thing like... but that's just a technical
question. Maybe from the moment it's finished or you deliver it, then
the clock starts ticking. Okay, but that's the one question is like
how do you determine when the clock starts ticking? But the other
is maybe it's a fundamentally different arrangement and therefore you wouldn't transgress.
Now why would it be fundamentally different? So if you were looking
at it from a moral perspective, you could say that the power
dynamics are very different between קבלנות kablanut and employer-employee. Even if you're
an employee with a nice paycheck, you know,
you
get... If you basically are building a cabinet and you know for
me, you're much more like the boss, right? You chose to take
the job, you're working for yourself, you did your whatever, you know,
maybe I as the customer am not going to be happy because
you're not getting it done on time and so on, you know,
but nevertheless the power dynamics are very different in a קבלנות kablanus
type of a perspective. That's like from the moral perspective why it
could be different. The גמרא Gemara also looks at it, you know,
obviously from the halachic perspective. So let's look at the גמרא. Gemara.
And there is some parallel between the moral issue here and the
halachic issue. Okay, קבלנות kablanus עובר משום בל תלין או אינו עובר
משום בל תלין? over mishum bal talin o eino over mishum bal
talin? אומן קונה בשבח כלי, uman koneh b'shvach kli, בשבח כלי b'shvach
kli excuse me, והלואה היא? v'hovo hi?
Do we say that when actually I'm building this cabinet for you,
I own the improvement of it? You gave me the raw materials,
you gave me the wood, and they were worth ten dollars. Now
I've built this cabinet, it's worth a thousand dollars. So you own
ten dollars of this cabinet and I own nine hundred and ninety
dollars of this cabinet. I put in all of the improvement. It's
my improvement. This thing now is everything that I contributed to it
is mine. And when you pay me for it, you're buying it
off of me. You're buying my nine hundred and ninety dollar sort
of stake in this cabinet off of me. Okay, and therefore it's
not a שכירות s'chirus at all, it's more like a purchase. Okay,
so the גמרא Gemara says והלואה היא. v'halvo'ah hi. Now it should
really say מכר היא, mecher hi, but what it means by הלואה
halvo'ah is, if you don't pay me for it when I deliver
it, I've delivered this cabinet, you don't pay me right away, what
I'm basically doing is I'm letting you owe me the money that
you need to pay me for the cabinet. But it's not that
you haven't paid me my wages, it's that I gave you this
cabinet, you owe me money for it because it was a type
of a מכר mecher transaction, and I say, you know what, you
can pay me later, so essentially you took a loan from me.
Okay, but it's not שכירות, s'chirus, that's one way of saying it.
או, o, or do we say אין אומן קונה בשבח כלי? ein
uman koneh b'shvach kli? No, no, no, you don't gain the improvement,
you built this up, now this is all mine, this thousand dollar
cabinet, and I only owe you the amount that we originally agreed
upon that I would pay you for your, you know, for your
work. But I own the whole thing, I just have to pay
you for your work. So in that type of a case, it's
a שכירות. s'chirus. Okay, שכירות היא, s'chirus hi, and it's a שכירות.
s'chirus.
So אמר ליה רב ששת, amar lei Rav Sheshet, so ששת Sheshet
said to whoever it is who asked him this question, I'm sorry,
אומן עובר בשבח כלי? uman over b'shvach kli? I want to understand
this. So let's let's say if some kind of arrangement I have,
you know, you hire me to renovate your apartment but you're paying
me weekly or whatever it is, right? Then it's not קבלנות. kablanus.
No, that's not קבלנות. kablanus. קבלנות kablanus is when you pay for
the job. But let's say you gave me the raw materials and
you're supposed to pay me weekly and you haven't, am I allowed
to keep the raw materials? Huh? In other words, you gave me,
you know, you're supplying materials, you know, and I'm going to put
it in your apartment and build it in. That's a different question.
Yeah, that's a different question, maybe you are because, you know, in
a sense that's like a question of תפיסה, tfisa, you're just grabbing
onto my property to get paid. That's a completely different question. So
let's see what ששת Sheshet said. אמר ליה רב ששת עובר. amar
lei Rav Sheshet over. He does transgress, which presumably means אין אומן
קונה בשבח כלי. ein uman koneh b'shvach kli. That you don't really,
it really is just I'm paying you for your work, it's not
that I'm buying the new object off of you. So it's a
problem because elsewhere רב ששת Rav Sheshet seems to take the opposite
position, תוספות Tosafot discusses that. So the גמרא Gemara says והתניא אינו
עובר, v'h tanya eino over, but a ברייתא Baraita says you don't
transgress in a case of קבלנות. kablanus. התם שהמחהו אצל חנוני ואצל
שולחני, hatam she-himchihu etzel chanvani v'etzel shulchani, which is like, there to
there, that's not about קבלנות. kablanus. The ברייתא Baraita that says you
don't transgress has nothing to do with whether it's שכירות s'chirus or
קבלנות, kablanus, it had to do with the fact that you arranged
for somebody else to pay the guy, okay, which would be funny
if the ברייתא Baraita was specifically talking about קבלנות kablanus we'd say
that's not the point. All right, anyway, נימא מסייע ליה, neima mesayei
lei, let's try to support רב ששת Rav Sheshet that says you
do transgress.
הנותן טלית לאומן, hanoten talit l'uman, you give your טלית talit to
a craftsman, presumably you're hiring him to, I don't know, to put
on some nice embroidery, you know, type of a thing or whatever
you're hiring him to do, you know, to improve it. Okay, גמרה,
gamrah, now he finishes it. הודיעו, hodio, and he says, you know
what, it's done, come pick it up when you're ready. אפילו מכאן
ועד עשרה ימים אינו עובר משום בל תלין. afilu mi-kan v'ad asara
yamim eino over mishum bal talin. Even for ten days you're not
over, if you take ten days before you come and pick it
up because presumably the clock doesn't start ticking when it's done, the
clock starts ticking when you pick it up. We'll see. נתנה לו
בחצי היום, nasna lo b'chetzi hayom, but when he gave it to
you even if he gave it to you in the middle of
the day, מששקעה לו החמה עובר משום בל תלין. mishishka lo hachama
over mishum bal talin. That's like the גמרא's Gemara discussion, the משנה's
Mishnah discussion about שכיר שעות, s'chir sha'ot, that if he finishes in
the middle of the day you don't have, you only have the
next the remaining part of that day to pay him up. Okay,
so there the only issue here is when is the job done?
When does the clock start ticking? When the goods are delivered.
But nevertheless you see that it's that you're over, that it's considered
to be like normal שכירות, קבלנות sechirut kablanut and the same prohibition
applies. Presumably אין אומן קונה בשבח כלי. ein uman koneh b'shvach kli.
So the גמרא Gemara says like this, אי אמרת אומן קונה בשבח...
i-amarta uman koneh b'shvach... Okay so the only issue here is when
is the job done? When does the clock start ticking? When the
goods are delivered? But nevertheless you see that you're עובר, over, that
it's considered to be like normal שכירות s'chirus, קבלנות kablanus and the
same prohibition applies. Presumably אומן קונה בשבח כלי. uman koneh b'shevach kli.
So the גמרא Gemara says like this: ואי אמרת אומן קונה בשבח
כלי, v'ei amart uman koneh b'shevach kli, אמאי עובר? amai over? Why
you transgress? So you see רב ששת Rav Sheshet was right. You
do transgress because he's not קונה בשבח כלי, koneh b'shevach kli, it's
not a מכר, mecher, it's a normal type of שכירות. sechirut. So
אמר רב מרי בריה דרב כהנא amar Rav Mari brei d'Rav Kahana
says no, נימא בהיכי תימצא. neima b'heichi timtza. We're not talking about
every case, we're talking about a special case. What's the special case?
בגרדי דסרבלא b'garde d'sarvla with a type of a, type of a
cloak of like, of what do you call it, of like silk?
סרבלא Sarvla is silk? I thought סרבלא sarvla was like, does anybody
have an English? No. סרבלא Sarvla was like, like, like a linen
or something? Nobody has an English? What did, David, what did it
say? בגד דסרבלא, Baged d'sarvla, okay. It says the Rashi refers to,
may refer to teazling a thick cloth.
Thick cloth, okay. I mean the גמרא Gemara definitely has סרבלא sarvla
as something, yeah, it's not linen because linen you wear in the
summer. The גמרא Gemara has סרבלא sarvla as something you wear in
the winter. What? Overalls?
Yeah, yeah, so it's some type of a thick thing you wear
in the winter.
What? Overalls? Yeah, heavy, yeah, so that's clearly what it is. Okay,
some type of a thick cloth cloth. So big deal, why does
that make it a special case? So the גמרא Gemara says, למיא
יהבני עלה, l'maya yahavni ala, so the גמרא Gemara says so okay,
what's special about that? Because why do you give it to him?
לרוקעי, l'rukei, because you're not making something new, it's not like you're
putting on any embroidery, you're just like banging it and trumping and
tramping and trampling on it and softening it. It's like, it's a
type of a sackcloth and you're going to work it to make
it softer. So the גמרא Gemara says, okay, but it's still שבח
כלי, shevach kli, right? You've now made it a better item. Maybe
it's not so visible the difference, but you've made it a more
valuable item. It should be a normal case of קבלנות. kablanut. היינו
שבחא, hainu shvacha, that's
its שבח. shevach. No, לא צריכא דאגריה לביתושי בטושא בטשא בטשא במחטא.
lo tzricha d'agrei l'bitushei bitusha batsha batsha b'machta. No, no, you basically
hired him to like, you know, to bang on it, you know,
and, and with his for, you know, and you paid him like
for every hundred hits, bangs you do on it and you take
it out and you whack it in order to soften it. You're
paying him not as קבלנות, kablanut, you're paying him for, you know,
not for the whole job, for the finished improved item. You're paying
him either by the hour, by the number of hits that he,
you know, hits at every hundred hits I'll give you a dollar.
Okay, and therefore it's a normal שכירות. sechirut. So the גמרא Gemara
says you can't prove it from that case because we can say
that that case is שכירות sechirut and not קבלנות. kablanut. So we
can still have an open question whether קבלנות kablanut would apply this
law of, what would be the law of אומן קונה בשבח כלי
uman koneh b'shevach kli and whether the law of ביומו תתן שכרו
b'yomo titein secharo would apply. Okay, let's take a look now at
the עמוד ב. amud beis. Yes. What about the aspect that in
these cases the craftsman is in possession of the object? So I
mean he doesn't have to even return it unless he gets paid
in a way, right? Yeah, that's sort of similar to what Michael
says, so that raises questions about how what his type of, you
know, how he can sort of leverage his possession. Right, so that's
true, but that's like a, no, no, okay, but that's different than
the question about, you know, it's that's it's relevant, but it's a
different halachic question. Okay, שכיר בזמנו נשבע ונוטל. schir bizmano nishba v'notel.
Now we move on to the second part of the משנה Mishnah
which has nothing to do with the prohibition of, well it's not
nothing, but it's not about the prohibition of paying on the right
time. It's a separate rabbinic הלכה halacha that, you know, you see
this happens all the time. I come to my employer and I
say pay me and he said I already paid you, right? So
how do we, how do we work that out in בית דין?
Beis Din? What would that normally be in בית דין? Beis Din?
That would be a כופר בהכל, kofer b'hakol, right? And he'd be
פטור. patur. Okay, so that sort of puts me in a very
disadvantaged position, not only because of, you know, unscrupulous employers, even just
people that are just not able to keep track of all the
million details, right? And they assume that they did pay me and
they didn't, right? I will know much better whether I've been paid
or not and whether he paid me even if he's trying to
tell the truth. Okay, but if he thinks he's paid me, it
becomes a כופר בהכל, kofer b'hakol, whatever, so חזל Chazal established that
I can make a שבועה shvua that I haven't been paid and
I can get and I can get paid in that case. Okay,
and but that is only during this זמנו, zmano, during this period
when I normally would be paid. Because as we'll see in a
minute, I mean not to ruin what the גמרא Gemara is going
to say, but if I waited, I finished at the end of
the day and I didn't come to demand it until the next
morning, there's something a little strange, right? I was supposed to get
paid sometime that night. And if I waited to, to raise the
issue until the next morning, we're starting to wonder a little bit
is it really true that I haven't been paid? If I really
hadn't been paid, right, I would have started, I would have asked
for it during the time when I'm supposed to expect to get
paid. So if I make my demand during the time I'm supposed
to get paid, I make a שבועה shvua and I can collect.
Okay, so let's take a look at the
גמרא. Gemara. He has to be at least here in front of
two people and say, listen, so yeah, we'll get to that. שכיר,
schir, אמאי תקנו ליה רבנן
למישבע ולמשקל? amai tiknu leih rabanan l'mishba u'lmishkal? Why do rabbis say
I can take a שבועה shvua and collect? אמר רב יהודה אמר
שמואל הלכות גדולות שנו כאן. amar Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel halachot gedolot
shanu kan. Here we have a very big הלכה. halacha. Okay, it's
interesting like, by the way, it's the name of a major Geonic
work called הלכות גדולות. Halachot Gedolot. Anyway, so the גמרא, Gemara, although
elsewhere תוספות Tosafot points out it uses that phrase to talk about
like a very important תקנה, takana, maybe it's big because it changes
the way דאורייתא d'oraisa it would have been, דאורייתא d'oraisa the employer
would have taken a שבועה, shvua, here the employee takes a שבועה,
shvua, maybe it's a big deal because it's very important for the
whole nature of It's a type of phrase הלכתא רבתא
דשבועה. hilcheta ravata deshvua. Right, exactly. But here the גמרא Gemara does
this type of very picky עיון iyun type of an issue about
the phrase used. So אמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל amar Rav Yehuda
amar Shmuel הני הלכתא נינו hani hilchata ninu what are these
הלכות? halachot? תקנתא נינו takanata ninu they're תקנה takana mean הלכה halacha
you know is maybe something that the רש״י Rashi says הלכה למשה
מסיני halacha l'moshe mi-Sinai or more refers to a detail of a
law within an existing type
of a framework or system as opposed to a clear rabbinic edict
to change the way things are being done. So אלא אמר רב
יהודה אמר שמואל תקנתא גדולה שנו כאן. ela amar Rav Yehuda amar
Shmuel takanata gedola shanu kan. Fine, there's a big תקנה. takana. גדולות
gedolot what do you mean big?
מכלל דאיכא קטנות mikal d'ika ktanot what are there small תקנות? takanot?
What does it mean this is a big one? Fine, that's just
funny גמרא Gemara what's bother you. אלא אמר רב פפא אמר שמואל
תקנתא קבועה שנו כאן. ela amar Rav Papa amar Shmuel takanata kvua
shanu kan.
You know like an established תקנה takana which means that
basically get back to the earlier point: they're very important, okay? They're
doing a really important thing for society and they're a really strong
תקנה. takana. Okay, fundamental, maybe a way of saying it. רש״י Rashi
says ראוי לקבען. raui likovan. You have to make sure like that
this should be a regular part of your economic system. תקנתא דשבועה
שנו כאן. takanata d'shvua shanu kan.
שבועה דבעל הבית היא shvua d'baal habayit hi because look at how
what a big deal it was. The בעל הבית baal habayit really
had the obligation to take this שבועה. shvua. He was a כופר
הכל. kofer hakol. Now you could say כופר הכל kofer hakol he
should not pay and not even have to take a שבועה. shvua.
Okay, well maybe שבועת היסת shvuat hesset although other גמרא Gemara sounds
like he had a שבועה דאורייתא. shvua d'Oraita. So this gets a
whole discussion in מסכת שבועות. Masechet Shvuot. But some say that even
if he was a מודה במקצת modeh b'miktzat even if he basically
says you're right I haven't paid you you are owed $100 for
today, you're right I didn't pay you everything but I did pay
you 50, and even in that case he's a מודה במקצת modeh
b'miktzat should take a שבועה דאורייתא shvua d'Oraita should take a שבועה
shvua that he didn't pay the other 50, that he did pay
already 50. We let the employee take the שבועה shvua and get
paid. So even in a case where it's a real שבועת התורה
shvuat ha-Torah that the בעל הבית baal habayit should take, he's the
one that's being made the demand of, he should take the שבועה
shvua and להיפטר l'hipater okay? Nevertheless, עקרוה רבנן לשבועה מבעל
הבית akruha rabanan lishvua m'baal habayit they uprooted it from the בעל
הבית baal habayit ושדיוה אשכיר v'shadyuha a-sachir and they placed it on
the שכיר sachir on the employee. משום כדי חייו דשכיר mishum k'dei
chayav d'sachir because this guy's got to make a living, right? And
so what, doesn't mean he can steal from people? The גמרא Gemara
says ומשום כדי חייו דשכיר נפסיד ליה לבעל הבית? u-mishum k'dei chayav
d'sachir nafsid lei l'baal habayit? Just in order because this guy's got
to make a living we make the בעל הבית baal habayit lose?
I mean there's a question about justice, right? We're not doing לפנים
משורת הדין. lifnim mishurat hadin. So no, בעל הבית גופיה ניחא ליה
דמשתבע שכיר ושקיל כי היכי דליגרו ליה פועלים. baal habayit gufei nicha
lei d'mishtava sachir v'shakil ki heichi d'ligru lei poalim.
So this here's the גמרא Gemara sort of talks about this is
what I was thinking before when I spoke about the גמרא Gemara
getting into the realities of the economic system. In some way this
system is in everybody's best interest because the owner knows that if
the שכיר sachir doesn't have the opportunity to take a שבועה shvua
and collect, that people will not want to work because they're going
to afraid that they're going to be cheated out of their wages.
So it's not like you particularly when you know you're telling the
truth and you're forced to pay the guy who's lying and take
a שבועה, shvua, you don't like this תקנה. takana. So not in
this particular case but as a class it's in the interest of
employers that this תקנה takana be
around because otherwise they'll scare off all the workers.
I gave you the end. I ruined the surprise. Anyway, at least
the גמרא Gemara said כי היכי דליגרו ליה פועלים ki heichi d'ligru
lei poalim because then workers will hire themselves out. So the גמרא
Gemara says שכיר גופיה ניחא ליה דמשתבע בעל הבית ואיפטר כי היכי
דליגרוהו בעל הבית. sachir gufei nicha lei d'mishtava baal habayit v'ipatar ki
heichi d'ligruhu baal habayit.
What do you mean? Say the opposite argument. That if the employees,
the workers would want the בעל הבית baal habayit to take a
שבועה shvua because if they have too much power, the employees, if
they can take too much advantage of the בעל הבית, baal habayit,
he won't hire them. Okay? כי היכי
דליגרוהו ki heichi d'ligruhu in order that they should be hired. Okay?
So you have to strike the right balance, right? If you protect
one side too much, there's going to be consequence to that תקנה
takana that's going to throw things out of whack. So you still
don't understand why you're protecting the workers, protect the בעל הבית, baal
habayit, it's in you could make the same argument that it's in
the employee's interest. So the גמרא Gemara says לא, בעל הבית על
כורחיה אגר. lo, baal habayit al korchei agar. At the end of
the day he's got a field that needs to be plowed. So
worker protection laws are ultimately not going to stop him from hiring
out workers, he needs to hire them out. So we're going to
protect the worker. So the גמרא Gemara says אי נמי שכיר על
כורחיה אוגר. i nami sachir al korchei ogar. I don't understand, people
need a job.
So if you protect the בעל הבית baal habayit it doesn't mean
that they won't hire themselves out, they need to put food on
the table. So you still haven't explained assuming that we don't assume
one side is going to be more honest or one side's going
to be more dishonest, it's just a question about what to do
here that's going to sort of be a תקנה takana that will
work for everybody, you haven't explained why it makes more sense to
protect the workers than to protect the owner. So the גמרא Gemara
says אלא ela fine,
it's not a question
about about... about what do you call it, about like which תקנה
takanah will work and which, you know, within society, it's a question
about which one will get the most just results. Why is that?
אלא בעל הבית טרוד בפועליו הוא. ela Balabayis tarud b'poalav hu. The
בעל הבית Balabayis has a thousand workers. You know, you're, you know,
if you've been paid or not, right? I mean, you know, I
don't know, I can't remember if I've paid you, I have a
thousand different workers. So therefore, it's more likely, if somebody's going to
be dishonest, it'd be either way. We don't assume that employers are
more dishonest or employees are more dishonest. But people make honest mistakes.
Okay, and we're more afraid the בעל הבית Balabayis makes honest mistakes,
so we give the power to the worker. Okay, says גמרא: Gemara:
אי הכי נשקליה בלא שבועה. ei hachi nishklei belo shvua. If that's
what we think happened, if we want to assume that everybody is
trying to do the right thing and people make an honest mistake,
why do you have them make a שבועה? shvua? So there's an
obvious answer, because then you're just opening a door for the for
the people that will lie, right? You know, once you say you
can collect it without a שבועה, shvua, then that just puts out
the welcome mat for the dishonest people. But the גמרא Gemara sort
of frames it a little differently: כדי להפיס דעתו של בעל הבית.
kdei l'hafis da'aso shel Balabayis.
I think I paid, I realize I could have made an honest
mistake, but I'll feel better about the whole situation if you make
a שבועה. shvua. And then I can say, 'Okay, you know what?
I probably just misremembered.' Right? So it helps me not be upset
about the situation. And what it also does is it helps try
to limit it that only honest people are going to, you know,
sort of do this and not dishonest people. Okay, so the גמרא
Gemara says וניתביה, unitvei, yeah, so it says שבועה's shvua happening like
in בית דין. Beis Din. Right, so he's like taking him, like
people get to בית דין Beis Din that same day? Oh well,
so the point is you have to make the, you have to
act to be paid that day, you don't have to have the
court case that day. Right, so that's what the משנה Mishnah says.
If you were תובע בזמנו, toveia bizmano, then you have a right
to collect
even take your שבועה shvua even later. But you have to have
made the demand during that period. Yeah, then you'll have to be
able to prove it. You'll have to have עדים edim that you
made that demand, like it would only be cases where you have
עדים. edim. Like I can't imagine someone like rushing to get עדים.
edim.
Right, the way the משנה Mishnah says it's at a time when
you would need עדים. edim. Right, right, right, it's true, it's true.
Okay. I mean, or once you set up the system though, there
are plenty of, you know, then you don't necessarily every case doesn't
have to come to court. You come to me and I say
no, I think I already paid you, you say you didn't, so
you'll say, you know, I'll take the—of course, if you do that
without עדים, edim, then I can later deny that you did the
whole thing. So you could take the שבועה shvua outside? I have
to check. I imagine you could. You know, and the only question
would be would be whether I could then later deny it. But
assuming that we're all honest people and we want to avoid the
court or whatever, right, then we could probably, I have to double
check. Okay. We discussed all these cases in such a dispassionate intellectual
way about ideas and law ideas. People are angry at each other,
taking each other to court and there's that whole dimension to it
which must—right, but I think the thing that I just said was
גמרא Gemara doesn't mean just because you have a legal recourse here
that you have to get to court.
Once the rules are clear, hopefully then there's a way of dealing
with it, you know? So, alright. So now the גמרא Gemara says
like this: Okay, וניתביה ליה באהדי סהדי. unitvei lei be'adei sahadei.
So now the גמרא Gemara says why don't we just say that
you have to be paid in front of witnesses? Meaning we might
say make sure there's a receipt, okay? Or something like that. Why
isn't there another way of dealing with it? So if I come
and I say you paid me—you didn't pay me and you say
yes I did, we would say okay bring the witnesses. Okay, anytime
you paid without witnesses, you would be considered that you hadn't paid,
and that would always so that's a way of protecting my interest,
right? Just make sure that you always pay with witnesses, so then
I'd always be believed if you couldn't bring witnesses to prove you
paid. So the גמרא Gemara says no: טרחא דמילתא. tircha d'milsa.
That's too much of a demand on the בעל הבית Balabayis to
demand that he pays all of his workers he brings witnesses with
him all the time. And then you have to say what about
having a receipt? What?
So having a receipt is not too much of a demand? So
we could have switched it,
we could have said what wait, how would that work? I give
you your wages and you give me a receipt. I the worker
give you the receipt. That's also a טרחא. tircha. Well, first of
all, you have to understand that many people were not literate and
couldn't write you anything. So
yeah, but then you would have you could be it could be
forged or whatever. Okay, וניתביה ליה מעיקרא. unitvei lei me'ikara. So why
don't you just prepay? If the whole reason for this is because
people are too busy when it comes time to pay, why don't
you just pay at the beginning of the day? Now, who says
you're not טרחא tircha at the beginning of the day? You have
a hundred workers at the beginning of the day also. Anyway, the
גמרא Gemara says I don't get why that was necessarily better: שניהם
רוצים בהקפה. shneyehm rotzin b'hakafa. No, both of them want to be
paid at the end of the day. You the בעל הבית Balabayis
want to obviously want to delay the time you have to pay,
and I the worker, I'm going to be out in your field
for eight hours, I don't want to have the money in my
pocket, like it'll fall out, or whatever, who knows, somebody will steal
it from me, I'd rather get the money right before I'm about
to go home. Okay, אי הכי אפילו קצץ נמי. ei hachi afilu
katzatz nami. Now if this is the reason because we're afraid the
בעל הבית Balabayis will make an honest mistake, that... should be that
I should be that the worker should be able to make a
שבועה shvua even if there's an issue about what amount we agreed
upon. Okay, and this is a different issue, let's say the question
isn't whether I've been paid, but what did we agree upon in
terms of my wages and we have slightly different memories about that.
Okay, אלמה תניא alma tanya why do we teach in a ברייתא
braitah אומן אומר שתים קצצת לי uman omer shtayim katzatzta li I
say you agreed to pay me two dollars for today, בעל הבית
אומר לא קצצתי לך אלא אחת ba'al habayit omer lo katzatzti lecha
ela achat I only agreed to pay you a dollar. המוציא מחברו
עליו הראיה. hamotzi mechavero alav haraya. So I lose out, I can't
prove it. Now תוס' Tos says you would have to make a
שבועה shvua במודה במקצת, bamodeh bemiktzat, but nevertheless, even if you make
a שבועה shvua because you're מודה במקצת, modeh bemiktzat, I don't have
the right to make a שבועה shvua and collect, that's not included
in שבועות shvuas in the שבועת השכיר. shvuat hasachir. Why not?
Maybe you're טרוד tarud and you forgot? I think there's an obvious
answer. You're not טרוד tarud in terms of what wages you've agreed
to pay. Like whether I've actually paid, which person I've paid, a
thousand people are coming to me at the end of the day,
but in terms of my basic you know salary that I pay
my workers. Of course, if I make a separate deal with each
person, you know we're always haggling, each worker I make a separate
deal. Anyway, the גמרא Gemara wants to know why does it not
apply here as well? Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says קצץ ודאי
מדכר דכר ליה אינשי. katzatz vadai midkar dakar lei inshi. Does that
mean you don't? It means yeah, yeah, you don't. The שכיר sachir
goes away without any money. Or no he just gets the one?
Yes, he gets the one. Okay, the גמרא Gemara says so that's
what the גמרא Gemara basically says קצץ ודאי מדכר דכר ליה אינשי.
katzatz vadai midkar dakar lei inshi. No, no, no, people remember the
salary arrangement that they agreed to, they don't remember if they paid
or not, but they agreed what salary they set. Okay, אי הכי
ei hachi says גמרא Gemara אפילו עבר זמנו נמי. afilu avar zmano
nami. Okay, if this is why this is true, because I'll forget
you know and be distracted or whatever, why don't you the worker
have a right to collect even and make your שבועה shvua even
if you come two days later? Why does this power to make
the שבועה shvua only apply during the next time period, the immediately
following time period? אלמה תנן alma tnan why do we teach in
the משנה mishna עבר זמנו אינו נשבע ונוטל? avar zmano eino nishba
venotel? After that you know night time or after the daytime after
the next time period, you can no longer do it. So the
גמרא Gemara says I mean you have to make the demand during
that immediate next time period. גמרא Gemara says no חזקה אין בעל
הבית עובר משום בל תלין. chazaka ein ba'al habayit over mishum bal
talin. No, no, no, because we're going to assume that if the
time period passed, I definitely would have paid it. Here's where the
מצוה mitzvah comes in. Because this is why it's defined by the
מצוה mitzvah of paying. Since I have a מצוה mitzvah to pay
you during that time period, if we're now it's the next morning,
you were supposed to be paid at night, and I say I
did pay you, we're going to presume that I'm telling the truth.
Because presumably I would not have transgressed the prohibition of delaying it
that long. So you know I'm טרוד tarud I remembered to pay.
Yeah, that's the funny thing. So that's the גמרא's Gemara next question,
you channeled the גמרא. Gemara. והאמרת בעל הבית טרוד בדאגתו הוא? veha'amarta
ba'al habayit tarud bid'agato hu? But one minute, he's distracted! He's distracted!
Just because he has a מצוה mitzvah to pay on time doesn't
mean that he remembers exactly. גמרא Gemara says no הני מילי מקמי
דלימטי זמן חיובא. hanei milei mikamei delimti zman chiyuva. I'm too distracted
before there's going to be a consequence. Like at the time like
everybody's asking to be paid or whatever, you know, I'm not yet
paying or I haven't yet like totally paid full attention to exactly
who I've paid or I haven't paid. אבל מטי זמן חיובא aval
mati zman chiyuva once if I haven't paid by the end of
the night, I'm going to have transgressed, I'm going to take time
to like focus and realize like who I've paid, who I haven't
paid. Okay, רמי אנפשיה ומדכר rami anafshei umidkar I make myself remember.
So now the גמרא Gemara says okay, so we're saying that because
I wouldn't transgress you know we assume that at this stage I'm
telling the truth. So the גמרא Gemara says וכי שכיר עובר משום
בל תגזול? vechi sachir over mishum bal tigzol? So if everybody is
honest, so this guy the שכיר sachir certainly knows if he's been
paid or not. So is he trying to steal consciously steal because
that's what you have to say. If you assume the בעל הבית
ba'al habayit is telling the truth, you're assuming the שכיר sachir is
lying and the שכיר sachir knows! So the שכיר sachir really would
you think he would consciously be lying? So גמרא Gemara says no
התם תרי חזקי והכא חד חזקה. hatam terei chazakei vehacha chad chazaka.
It's two against one. גבי בעל הבית איכא תרי חזקי. gabei ba'al
habayit ika terei chazakei. There's two reasons to assume the בעל הבית
ba'al habayit is telling the truth at this stage. חדא דאין בעל
הבית עובר משום בל תלין chada de'ein ba'al habayit over mishum bal
talin number one is by that time he wouldn't have transgressed בל
תלין bal talin וחדא דאין שכיר משהה שכרו vechada de'ein sachir masheh
scharo
and now we're not saying the בעל הבית ba'al habayit won't be
over on לא תגזול lo tigzol because the בעל הבית ba'al habayit
is not necessarily consciously stealing. But there's so that's not a relevant
point. Okay, but there's two reasons to say that he's right. Number
one is he wouldn't have waited that long and number two the
employee wouldn't have waited that long. Why did it take you so
long to ask? Right, what's going on there? We're skeptical whether you
you say you haven't been paid yet? Yeah, what employee waits so
long to ask? I mean you were paid and you're coming back
for second helpings, you know. So there's two reasons even if he
doesn't know whether he's even if there's a doubt whether he you
know doesn't remember or not, there's two arguments here to assume that
he's telling the truth. Okay, he wouldn't have waited and the employee
wouldn't have waited. והכא חדא חזקה vehacha chada chazaka here
the employee only has one thing on his side. That we assume
I wouldn't consciously lie. Okay, so it's therefore and in those cases
we say you don't have the right to take the שבועה, shvua,
the בעל הבית ba'al habayit it's like a normal כופר הכל kofer
hakol and he walks away and doesn't pay you. מודה במקצת modeh
bemiktzat he would take a שבועה. shvua. Let's finish the משנה. mishna.
אם יש עדים שתבעו הרי זה נשבע ונוטל *im yesh edim she-tva'o
harei ze nishba ve-notel*. If there are witnesses, here are your witnesses,
Jenna, that the demand was made during the right time, then you
can make your שבועה *shvua* at any time, as long as you
demand it during the right time. Okay, so the גמרא *Gemara* says
והא תבעו לקמן *ve-ha tva'u lekaman*. So the גמרא *Gemara* says, I
don't understand what the benefit of witnesses is. The גמרא *Gemara* was
assuming that the גמרא *Gemara* doesn't yet realize that you demanded in
the right time. The גמרא *Gemara* just says there were witnesses that
you demanded. So who cares if there were witnesses you demanded? You
could be demanding in front of בית דין *Beis Din* and you
waited too long. So the גמרא *Gemara* says no. אמר רב אשי
*Amar Rav Ashi* meaning you're making the demand in front of us
and we say that it's too late.
Witnesses are that it was during the right time, but that wasn't
explicit in the משנה *Mishna*. So the גמרא *Gemara* says אמר רב
יוסף אף על פי שתבעו בזמנו *Amar Rav Yosef af al pi
she-tva'u bizmano*. No, the point is the witnesses show you made it
in the right time, then you're allowed to postpone to collect whenever
you collect by making the שבועה *shvua*. ודילמא לבתר הכי פרע *u-dilma
levatar hachi para*. So okay, how do you know now that maybe
the guy paid up after the demand was made and before the
whole case came to בית דין *Beis Din*? Since part of the
whole dynamics was about he's not always he's at that that he
doesn't wait, so
once the period is over he focuses and he remembers and he'll
pay, so maybe that happened now that it's been a while since
the demand was made. So the גמרא *Gemara* says אמר אביי שתבעו
כל זמנו *Amar Abaye she-tva'u kol zmano*. No, they kept on asking
and demanding until the end of the period, which is a very
funny case. It's not just I asked you at 8:00 PM. I
asked you again at 10:00 and at 12:00 and at 4:00
and at 5:00 AM and all those times, so I need witnesses
the entire time because otherwise you'll say I paid you by the
time the time was over, which makes it completely moot. So the
גמרא *Gemara* says ולעולם *u-le'olam*? And if he did that, can he
really go ahead now and two years later make a שבועה *shvua*?
Maybe eventually the owner paid. What is the limit to this תקנה
*takana*? Because again it's just a תקנה *takana*. Fundamentally the owner is
a כופר הכל *kofer hakol* and should walk away free. So the
גמרא *Gemara* says אמר רב חמא בר עוקבא כנגד אותו היום של
תביעה *Amar Rav Chama bar Ukva kineged oto hayom shel tvi'ah*. No,
basically he gets one more day. Okay, so if he made the
demand, the way the גמרא *Gemara* says it at the end of
the day and can prove it, then he gets another day to
go ahead and collect in בית דין *Beis Din* and make his
שבועה *shvua*. But what if he continued demanding it? That's a good
question. I don't know. Okay, we'll end here. They had to get
support now.